A Haskell module for sound Ghilbert-style proofs

Author: | Marnix Klooster <marnix.klooster@gmail.com>
Copyright: | GPL version 2 or later
Note: | This is a work in progress. Correctness and completeness not guaranteed. You have been warned!

(This document is usually available in two formats: XHTML and literate Haskell.)

Introduction

Here is the suggested interface for a small Haskell module that implements the Ghilbert-based core proof language, which I suggested to Raph Levien (personal e-mail, 30 May 2006). This module could be the core of a Ghilbert verifier:

> module HghCore

Some understanding of Metamath and/or Ghilbert is useful, but this document is intended to be reasonably self-contained.

The code in this document has been tested under GHC 6.4.2, but could very well work with other Haskell systems as well. To actually make this document work like a 'literate Haskell module', the order of this document is sometimes forced a bit.

Overview

This module provides an encapsulated data type

>       (Derivation

with accessors

>       ,sourceRules, targetRule

together with a very limited way of creating values of this type:

>       ,interpretProof

This function takes a

>       ,Proof(Hypothesis, RuleApp)

which is essentially the same as a Ghilbert proof. interpretProof then computes the resulting 'thm' (the 'target inference rule' of the Derivation). What Ghilbert calls a 'thm' or a 'stmt', we call an

>       ,InferenceRule, mkInferenceRule, ruleDVRs, ruleHypotheses, ruleConclusion

interpretProof also keeps track of all inference rules that are used by the proof (the 'source inference rules' of the Derivation).

Part of an InferenceRule is a set of 'disjoint variable restrictions':

>       ,DVRSet, mkDVRSet

All this is based on LISP-like expressions, just like GHilbert:

>       ,Expression(Var, App)
>       )
> where

We will need some auxiliary functionality from standard modules:

> import Data.List(sort, nub, (\\))

Expressions and inference rules

All mathematical expressions are constructed from variables and operators (=constants):

> data Expression = Var VarName | App ConstName [Expression]
>       deriving (Eq, Show)

with

> type VarName = String
> type ConstName = String

(TODO: Make these into real datatypes, so that we have real typechecking.)

An InferenceRule represents how to get from source expressions (hypotheses) to a target expression (the conclusion).

> data InferenceRule = InferenceRule
>       {ruleDVRs :: DVRSet
>       ,ruleHypotheses :: [Expression]
>       ,ruleConclusion :: Expression
>       }
>       deriving (Eq, Show)

(TODO: Create a custom Show instance, so that we more understandable output during debugging.)

Two InferenceRule objects are equal (under Eq) iff they have the same DVRSet, the same hypotheses (in the same order, including potential duplicates), and the same conclusion.

Note that the constructor for this data type is not exported, so that we can choose an optimal data structure for performance. Therefore we need a very simple constructor function:

> mkInferenceRule :: DVRSet -> [Expression] -> Expression
>                       -> InferenceRule
> mkInferenceRule dvrSet hyps concl = InferenceRule dvrSet hyps concl

Here we use the data type DVRSet, for which we only export the type

> data DVRSet = DVRSet [(VarName, VarName)]
>       deriving (Eq, Show)

To create a DVRSet the constructor function mkDVRSet is used. This function makes sure that two DVRSets are equal (under Eq) if they have the same restrictions, where duplicates are ignored, and ("x","y") is the same as ("y","x"). It does that by keeeping the DVRs in an InferenceRule in canonical order, with duplicates removed, and each pair ordered:

> mkDVRSet :: [(VarName, VarName)] -> DVRSet
> mkDVRSet = DVRSet . nub . sort . Prelude.map sortPair
>       where sortPair (p, q)
>               | p <= q = (p, q)
>               | True = (q, p)

Because of the canonical representation of an InferenceRule, the implementation of Eq InferenceRule is as simple as "deriving Eq" (as is done above).

Proofs

Now on to proofs:

> data Proof
>       = Hypothesis Expression
>       | RuleApp [Proof] [Expression] InferenceRule
>       deriving (Eq, Show)

TODO: Explain what the components of a RuleApp mean, and what it means for a RuleApp to be consistent.

Design Issue. As written, a RuleApp requires knowledge of the order of the hypotheses of an InferenceRule. However, (meta-)logically InferenceRule values that only differ in their order of hypotheses are equivalent. Therefore we have four options.

We specify the order of the result of ruleHypotheses to be the same as the creation order. We declare an InferenceRule with a different order of hypotheses to be different (under Eq). (We introduce a new equivalence (<==>) on InferenceRule, and by extension on Proof and Derivation (see below).) In a RuleApp the proofs must be in creation order.
We specify the order of the result of ruleHypotheses to be the same as the creation order. Two InferenceRule objects can have different ruleHypothese results, and still be the same (under Eq). (This seems to be inconsistent.) In a RuleApp the proofs must be in creation order.
We specify the order of the result of ruleHypotheses to be some arbitrary (but consistent) order. In a RuleApp the proofs must be in this same order.
Instead of [Proof], a RuleApp uses [(Expression, Proof)], where each Expression is the hypothesis that is proven by the corresponding sub-Proof. (Or we could even have it use a (Expression -> Proof), but that seems a bit silly.)

It seems each of these has its disadvantages. It seems the first option is the most consistent, while still making this module easy to use for a Ghilbert verifier. That's why I went with that option. (End of Design Issue.)

Deriving inference rules: Derivations

Now we come to the heart of the matter: the Derivation. A Derivation says: if these inference rules (the 'source rules') hold, then this inference rule (the 'target rule') holds as well.

> data Derivation = Derivation
>       {sourceRules :: [InferenceRule]
>       ,targetRule :: InferenceRule
>       }
>       deriving (Show, Eq) --TODO: implement a correct Eq

We do not export the constructors for the Derivation datatype, because we require that only 'true' derivations can be constructed by clients of this module. Therefore we will limit the ways in which Derivation objects can be created.

As a simple example, from the following two inference rules:

for all F, G and H, if G <-> H holds, then (F \/ G) <-> (F \/ H) holds
for all P and Q, if both P and P <-> Q hold, then Q holds

we can derive the following so-called derived inference rule:

for all F, G, and H, if both F \/ G and G <-> H hold, then F \/ H holds

For now the only function that results in a Derivation is interpretProof:

> interpretProof :: Proof -> Either String Derivation

This function basically implements the Ghilbert proof verification algorithm, with the DVRs computed just like Hmm does this for Metamath proofs. If the Proof is incorrect (i.e., if a RuleApp in it is inconsistent), then the result will be Left "some error message", otherwise the result will be a Right value with the resulting Derivation.

The simplest part of the Ghilbert proof algorithm is handling an Hypothesis:

> interpretProof (Hypothesis expr) =
>       Right $ Derivation
>               {sourceRules = []
>               ,targetRule = mkInferenceRule (mkDVRSet []) [expr] expr
>               }

In words: any hypothesis proves the simplest possible inference rule, namely that from any expression we can derive any expression.

RuleApp is the interesting case:

> interpretProof (RuleApp subproofs varExprs rule)

First we handle the inconsistent uses of RuleApp. There needs to be exactly one subproof per rule hypothesis:

>       | length (ruleHypotheses rule) /= length subproofs =
>               Left $ "TODO: nice error message"

TODO: for correctness,

check that subderivationsOrErrors has only Right values
check that substitutionsOrErrors has only Right values
check that substitution has no duplicate keys

If all of the above is correct, then the resulting Derivation

>       | True =
>               Right $ Derivation

has as its source rules, the current inference rule, together with those of its subderivations:

>                       {sourceRules = rule : concat (map sourceRules subderivations)

From the RuleApp Proof we can derive that the conclusion of the rule (after substitution) follows from all hypotheses of all subproofs:

>                       ,targetRule = let
>                               dvrs = mkDVRSet [] --TODO: implement
>                               hypotheses = concat $ map (ruleHypotheses . targetRule) subderivations
>                               conclusion = substApply substitution (ruleConclusion rule)
>                        in mkInferenceRule dvrs hypotheses conclusion
>                       }

In the above we used the following definitions:

>       where
>               subderivationsOrErrors = map interpretProof subproofs
>               subderivations = map (\(Right x) -> x) subderivationsOrErrors
>
>               subconclusions = map (ruleConclusion . targetRule) subderivations
>
>               substitutionsOrErrors :: [Either String Substitution]
>               substitutionsOrErrors = zipWith findSubstitution
>                                               (ruleHypotheses rule) subconclusions
>
>               substitution :: Substitution
>               substitution = fromRight $ substConcat
>                                       ( Substitution (zip (ruleLocalVars rule) varExprs)
>                                       : map (\(Right x) -> x) substitutionsOrErrors
>                                       )
>                       --Note that no substitution key duplication is possible
>                       --here, so we can use fromRight

Here the 'rule local variables' are those that only occur in its conclusion, and not in its hypotheses:

> ruleLocalVars :: InferenceRule -> [VarName]
> ruleLocalVars rule =
>       nub (varsOf (ruleConclusion rule))
>       \\ concat (map varsOf (ruleHypotheses rule))

See the appendix for the substitution functions.

This completes the implementation of the proof algorithm.

Two Derivation objects are equal (under Eq) iff they map the same set of InferenceRule to the same InferenceRule. This implies that a Derivation is independent of the Proof that was used to create it.

Open Issue. We could also make it possible to combine Derivation objects:

< combineDerivation :: Derivation -> Derivation -> Derivation

This takes the second derivation, removes from its sourceRules the targetRule of the first derivation, and adds to its sourceRules the sourceRules of the first derivation. Perhaps it sounds difficult, but basically this 'clicks together' derivations.

This combine operator is theoretically not necessary, since it is also possible to have a similar operator at the Proof level, and then interpretProof creates the desired Derivation. However, this requires one of the following:

Either a client of this module has to remember a Proof for each Derivation;
Or this module makes a Proof part of each Derivation.

Frankly I don't really like any of the three alternatives. The best alternative might be the first bullet above: implement the combine functionality outside of this core module, and keep Derivation and Proof separate. But I haven't decided yet. (End Open Issue.)

Weakening

Until now we've not been complete, in the technical sense: it is not possible to create every 'true' Derivation through interpretProof. The reason is that interpretProof computes the "strongest" inference rule that is proven by the given Proof. To do proper theorem verification à la Ghilbert, we need to be able to weaken a given derivation.

First, to determine the relationship between inference rules, we introduce

< (==>) :: InferenceRule -> InferenceRule -> Bool

Basically i ==> j ("i is at least as strong as j") iff i and j have the same conclusion, and if the DVRs and hypotheses of i are a subset (under (<==>)) of those of j.

Now we need the following two additional ways to create Derivations:

< strengthenSourceRules :: InferenceRule -> Derivation -> Derivation
< weakenTargetRule :: InferenceRule -> Derivation -> Derivation

strengthenSourceRule adds the given InferenceRule to the sourceRules, and removes any that are weaker (i.e., implied by it under (==>)). weakenTargetRule replaces the targetRule by the given InferenceRule, but only if the original rule implies the new one (otherwise an error occurs).

Appendix: helper functions

This appendix implements auxiliary functionality.

Expressions

The variables occurring in an expression are easily computed:

> varsOf :: Expression -> [VarName]
> varsOf (Var v) = [v]
> varsOf (App _c exprs) = concat $ map varsOf exprs

(Note that we do not remove duplicates here; each caller is responsible for that.)

Substitutions

A substitution describes how to map variables to expressions:

> data Substitution = Substitution [(VarName, Expression)]
>       deriving Show

Apply a substitution is simple:

> substApply :: Substitution -> Expression -> Expression
> substApply s@(Substitution m) (Var v) = case lookup v m of
>                               Just expr -> expr
>                               Nothing -> error $ "could not find " ++ show v ++ " in " ++ show s
> substApply s (App c exprs) = App c (map (substApply s) exprs)

It is equally simple to find a substitution from one expression to another:

> findSubstitution :: Expression -> Expression -> Either String Substitution
> findSubstitution (Var v) expr = Right $ Substitution [(v, expr)]
> findSubstitution expr1@(App _ _) expr2@(Var _) =
>       Left $ "cannot match " ++ show expr1 ++ " and " ++ show expr2
> findSubstitution expr1@(App c1 exprs1) expr2@(App c2 exprs2)
>       | c1 /= c2 =
>               Left $ "cannot match operators of " ++ show expr1 ++ " and " ++ show expr2
>       | length exprs1 /= length exprs2 =
>               Left $ "different arity in " ++ show expr1 ++ " and " ++ show expr2
>       | not allOk =
>               Left $ "no substitution found from " ++ show expr1 ++ " to " ++ show expr2
>               --TODO: add the Left values from substitutionsOrErrors
>       | True =
>               substitutionOrError
>               --TODO: if Left, add a Left error message saying which substitution is impossible
>       where
>               substitutionsOrErrors = zipWith findSubstitution exprs1 exprs2
>               allOk = allRight substitutionsOrErrors
>               substitutionOrError = substConcat $ map (\(Right x) -> x) substitutionsOrErrors

For now we implement substConcat in a very simple way:

> substConcat :: [Substitution] -> Either String Substitution
> substConcat = Right . Substitution . concat . map (\(Substitution m) -> m)

TODO: check for key duplication!

Error messages

> allRight :: [Either a b] -> Bool
> allRight [] = True
> allRight (Left _ : _) = False
> allRight (Right _ : rest) = allRight rest

Either

> fromRight :: Either a b -> b
> fromRight (Right b) = b
> fromRight (Left _a) = error "cannot apply fromRight to a Left value"

View document source. Generated on: 2006-11-03 10:29 UTC. Generated by Docutils from reStructuredText source.